No, I got to say I'm surprised by the
number of people that ask me that. Um
I don't think so.
I hope not.
Uh I don't think so. I think that
sometimes people feel like they don't
have control over the environment that
they're in. Yeah, which is why we get
that question so much. Yeah, and that
the society and the world has set them
up to fail.
I was uh I was on Capitol Hill today
and I was talking to somebody who's got
the authority to you know make things
happen.
And much of our conversation was about
how he just simply cannot make things
happen.
He should be able to
but the forces of resistance are so
strong.
He was talking about one
one issue in particular that as a not
just a senator but as a committee
chairman he should have the authority
just to you know
sign his name to a letter and something
should be done and he's like, "It's been
6 years and they just ignore me, ignore
me, ignore me." We're talking about the
CIA, NSA, FBI. They just ignore him.
And then they're like, "What are you
going to do about it? What are you going
to sue us?
Go ahead and sue us." And then he gets a
call from, you know, the the majority
leader saying, "Hey, cut it out. You're
making too many waves." He's like, "I'm
a freaking committee chairman."
So yeah, I I mean if even
the most important people in Washington
can't budge the CIA or the intelligence
community on on issues of you know
illegality
then we're all screwed. Well, I think
the average person kind of feels trapped
because there's so much news out there
and they're like, "All right, I see this
story that way and I see this story that
way." Then there's social media. Like,
how can people protect themselves from
this? Uh it's hard to protect yourself.
One of the questions that I get a lot on
my own podcast is what do you read in
the morning? And I go through this
laundry list. I get up hours earlier
than I probably need to just to read as
much as I can possibly cram into my head
every morning before I open my mouth to
start talking because I want to know
what's going on, but in order to learn
what's going on, you have to read,
you know, all sides of an issue cuz you
don't know who to trust, and then based
on your own
your own experience and your own
analysis come to a conclusion.
You know, time was where you could you
could
go to the Associated Press and feel
pretty confident that you knew what was
going on, and that's just not
the reality anymore. So, how can the
average person who's not as skilled as
as reading through BS like you are, how
can they read publications and try to
read between the fine lines and see
what's accurate and what's not? You you
have to you have to go to
all of the various ideological
perspectives. Like I read In fact, I'll
tell you exactly what I read. I'll I'll
call up my thing. I start off um
Washington Post, Wall Street Journal,
New York Times, LA Times,
Pittsburgh Post-Gazette just to get the
Steelers, Penguins, and Pirates news. Uh
CNN, AP, Fox, Politico, The Hill, the
New York Post. I read the Greek papers
just cuz I'm interested, and then I go
to the British press. I do The Times of
London, The Telegraph, The Guardian, the
London Evening Standard, BBC. Then I go
back to Dropsite News, Al Jazeera, The
Al-Monitor,
Electronic Intifada, Jerusalem Post, and
then I go a level down in in um
in uh
independent media. Consortium News, um
Axios,
Covert Action Magazine, Dropsite News.
You you you really have to read it all.
And so reading a variety of sources and
then like kind of sifting through a lot
of the stuff and then how can somebody
like okay this site's clearly lying or
this site's just clearly like creating
rage bait like
is it does it do you have do you have to
go and then compare it to another source
or is it just take time to learn what's
true and what's not? It it does take
time and I will say that I'm I'm a CIA
trained analyst so you're trained to
question everything. And so I
automatically do question everything.
You have to be very careful
not to fall into the trap of
automatically believing the outlets
whose ideologies most align with yours.
For example
at the start of COVID I absolutely
positively wanted to believe that this
was because the Chinese have the wet
market the Chinese eat bats the Chinese
don't wash their hands that it came from
the wet market from you know an aardvark
or whatever it is that they eat a
tamarind whatever.
And then I had to come to the conclusion
analytically that this was a lab leak
because that's where the evidence was
pointing.
And now I think the conventional wisdom
is that this was a lab leak. Now we have
to investigate whether it was leaked on
purpose or whether the lab was a
biological weapons lab or whether it was
a genuine
accident. We just don't know. And going
back to your story I know that you were
worked for the CIA for a long time then
you decided to come forward in that very
famous interview.
Like what was going through your mind
like what made you want to go public
even though you knew it would ruin your
career?
What finally did it for me was
comments over two two days from
President George W. Bush
that
there was no torture program. That was
on a Wednesday and then Friday he said
well if there is torture, it's because
of a rogue CIA officer."
And that's when I knew
that the agency was going to try to pin
it on me.
And so I decided to defend myself. And
then
when you came out, like what was going
through your mind? Did you know what was
about to unfold? You know what? I I
really believed at the time, quite
naively in in retrospect, that this was
a one-day story.
That it was going to run its course. I
would be, you know, famous or infamous
for for one day, and then everybody was
going to go back to their normal lives.
And that's not at all
what what happened.
You know, it just it took on a life of
its own.
It uh it it uh
lasted.
Uh it resulted in investigations.
It was just
it was just a unlike anything I had
anticipated. And then once you started
to open up, was there ever a moment
where you felt like you could have
pulled back and then stopped and
avoiding everything?
The funny thing is that
all the CIA had to do was call me and
tell me, "Stop."
Right? But they kept leaking stuff to
the to the post.
Where I would have to go back and defend
myself again.
All they had to do was say, "Just just
let's stop." And I would have stopped,
and none of this would have ever
happened.
But they're leaking to the post, leaking
to the post, leaking to the post. Then
they Then they escorted a friend of mine
out of the White House, and they accused
her of leaking um the information about
the secret prisons. She swore she didn't
do it, but they took her badge, they
suspended her security clearance, they
escorted her out of the White House,
told her never to come back. And I was
like, "Okay, so they're trying to
They're trying to ruin people now. I'm
going to defend myself."
And and so I did. And then what what
happened after that? I know you ended up
getting going to prison for that, right?
Yeah, I was charged initially with five
felonies, three counts of espionage, one
count of making a false statement, and
one count of violating the Intelligence
Identities Protection Act.
Um I hadn't committed espionage, and
they knew I hadn't committed espionage.
And so what they did
and it this wasn't specific to me, they
they do this to everybody. Um they
waited until they charged me with all
these multiple felonies, and then they
waited until I filed for bankruptcy,
and then they dropped the espionage
charges.
And then they come back and say, "Look,
you know, we can indict on other
charges. We're thinking of adding a um
conspiracy charge." And there was
another charge they said they were
considering. It was like uh it was a
second false statement charge of some
sort.
Or you can take a plea."
And they just grind you down, wear you
down until you're a little nub, and
you're broke, and you're looking at 12
to 18 years, or you can do the 23 months
that they're offering.
And so you take the deal.
And so you take the deal,
you go to prison.
Like what was going through your mind as
soon as as soon as those doors closed?
It's funny that you ask it that way. Um
and I and this is probably because of my
training, but
what was going through my mind was,
"You're trained for this. You can handle
this. You've been in far worse
situations than this."
And so I set out to Well, I actually
wrote a book about it.
The third printing is just out, Doing
Time Like a Spy.
I decided that I would use these 20
lessons that the CIA taught me,
beginning with make strategic alliances,
let others do your dirty work,
admit nothing, deny everything, make
counter accusations,
to ensure that I stayed safe and at the
top of the social heap.
So that's what I did.
So, people didn't look at you and think
you were like a snitch or anything. You
were able to kind of ride through that?
Yeah, thank thank God, but for a couple
of different reasons, two different
reasons. Number one,
God bless Mark Lanza Lotti.
You're not supposed to go to prison to
make friends.
I met Mark in prison,
and he has become like a brother to me,
one of my best friends in life.
Mark read in the New York Times on a
Sunday that I was coming to that prison
on Thursday. And out of the goodness of
his heart, he went to every single
Italian in the prison. And I mean
Italians named Gambino, Genovese,
Lucchese, you get the idea.
And he told them, "Listen, there's a CIA
guy coming here on Thursday. He's CIA,
not FBI. FBI is rats and cops. The CIA
protected us from the Muslims."
And so, the Italians welcomed me with
open arms, number one.
Number two, somehow,
and I have no idea how, this rumor got
around the Aryans that I was uh an
assassin for the CIA. And that after
9/11, I went around the world killing
Muslims.
They thought that was fantastic.
And so, I was okay with the Aryans. But
then, on the day that I arrived at the
prison,
the Nation of Islam newspaper carried a
statement from Louis Farrakhan
saying that I was a hero of the Muslim
people because I had stood up for Muslim
human rights.
And so, I had no problem with them
either, which only left the Mexicans.
And in my cell, we were in four-man
cells, but they would cram six men in
there.
Um four of the six were from the
Burachos, the Norteños, the Mexican
Mafia, and the Jalisco Cartel.
And one of them, the Buracho, he asked
me if I was educated and I said, "Yes."
He said, "Would you write my appeal?"
And I said, "Why, I'm not a lawyer."
"Yeah, but you're educated." I'm like,
"Sure. How hard could it be? Sure, I'll
write your appeal." So, I wrote his
appeal. We sent it in. It was denied,
but I didn't charge him anything.
And uh he asked me, "What do I owe you?"
I said, "Uh I I got I got people on the
outside. I don't need anything."
So, he put the word out among the
Mexicans that I was a good guy. I was
honest and that I uh helped him.
So, I didn't have The only problems I
ever had were with the the crooked,
illiterate, corrupt
guards. They were the only ones that
gave me any grief at all. And so, you
didn't have to do any like kind of CIA
tricks as far as reading people and
understanding
That's That's what the book's about. You
bet. And I'll give you an example,
actually.
Um
I'm proud of this book. This book won
two literary awards, but
but it makes me look like a very bad
guy. And I knew going into it, I was
going to just be honest and write the
truth and let people make judgments
based on on, you know, their own
beliefs. But I'll give you one example.
There was a uh
there was a serial killer in my uh
in my housing unit. We called him Truck.
He was a long-distance truck driver. And
in the days before
uh DNA testing,
he would he would pick up prostitutes at
uh
at truck stops and have sex with them
and then he would strangle them, so he
didn't have to pay them.
And then he would drive an hour or two
hours and then just throw their bodies
out of the side of the truck.
He finally got caught because he
strangled a woman, but she survived.
And she was able to give the cops the
license plate number. So,
he he was serving 40 years.
He was He had already done like 35
when I met him.
For whatever reason, reasons I never
understood, he constantly sought my
approval.
Hey John, I know you like the Steelers.
I saved you a seat in the in the day
room so you could watch the game. I'm
like, okay, thanks, Truck.
Hey John, I know you listen to classic
rock. There's a new classic rock
station, 1600 AM. I'm like, thank you,
Truck.
So, with that as background, there was
this other guy,
Cat in the Hat we called him cuz his
head was oddly elongated like like a
birth defect. And I had an empty bed in
my cell and he wanted to move in. Well,
we had this rule,
no pedophiles and no rats.
So, I said, are you a pedophile? He
said, no, I'm not a pedophile. I said,
what's your crime?
He says, murder for hire.
I said, I don't think I like that any
more than pedophilia.
So, I said, what were the circumstances?
He said, well, I was I was into the mob
for a hundred grand in in
in gambling and I I couldn't pay it. So,
I took a I took a life insurance policy
out on my business partner. I hired a
hit man to kill him.
And I said, let me think about it.
So, I went down to the law library and I
looked up his case. All of that was
true. What he didn't say was that in
order to save himself, he ratted out the
hit man.
And that's why he only got 20 years.
So, I said,
no rats are allowed in the cell.
Well, I'm in the day room one day. I'm
sitting next to Truck watching the
Steelers game. Cat in the Hat is
standing literally two feet away from
me.
Does not realize that I'm immediately
behind him. And earlier that day, I got
called to the lieutenant's office.
Usually when you get called to
lieutenant's office, it's because either
you're going to solitary or they want
you to rat somebody out.
I got called down because Jake Tapper
had driven up that day from CNN to
interview me and I had to sign a waiver.
So,
Cat in the Hat doesn't see me and he
says to the guy next to him, "Did you
hear Kiriakou got called down to the
lieutenant's office?" He goes, "That
guy's a rat. He got called down
to rat us out."
I didn't react at all.
And Truck said, "Did you hear that guy?
He just said you're a rat."
And then using my CIA training, I said
to Truck,
"Half an hour ago I heard him call you a
pedophile."
And without saying a word,
Truck got up and beat him almost to
death.
They had to land a helicopter
in the yard to life flight this guy to
Pittsburgh. Truck got 5 years added to
his sentence and he got sent back to a
medium security prison. 6 weeks later
Cat in the Hat came back.
And people had told him
what I had done.
So, he came back. He he wouldn't make
eye contact with me. He's like this.
He's like, "I'm sorry I called you a
rat. I I I should never have said that.
It wasn't true."
And I said, "Look at me."
I said, "As God is my witness,
if I ever hear my name cross your lips
ever again, you're dead.
And you'll never see it coming."
He's like, "I understand. I understand."
So, I very much used my CIA skills every
single day in prison. Sometimes it was
as simple as playing these moronic
guards off of each other. But usually it
was more serious. It was to keep myself
safe. And what did you do for the CIA?
Well, the first 7 and 1/2 years that I
was there, I was an analyst on the
Middle East. The second 7 and 1/2, I was
I was a counterterrorism operations
officer and I became the chief of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after 9/11.
Wow. It was it was serious duty. So, as
much as you can get into like what were
some of your roles and responsibilities?
Well, I mean, the basic responsibility
of any CIA officer is to recruit spies
to steal secrets. It's really that
simple.
In counterterrorism, it is to
infiltrate and destroy foreign terrorist
groups. And so, my my primary role in
Pakistan was to identify the locations
of Al-Qaeda's senior leadership and to
launch raids to to either kill or
capture them. And so, I led the raid
that resulted in the capture of Abu
Zubaydah, who we believed at the time
was the number three in Al-Qaeda. It was
the very first high-value capture. And
so, how, as far as stress goes, were you
more stressed during your time in prison
or when you were doing stuff like you
just described? Oh, yeah, prison was far
more stressful. That may not even really
make sense to most people.
It seems like you had a good you had a
good you had a good idea of how to work
the system in there. You had people on
your side. You knew how to
kind of manipulate people when you
needed to. So, why was prison more
stressful? For a couple of reasons.
Number one,
the guards and the administrators were a
wild card.
I mean, they could they can disappear
you if they want to. It's called diesel
therapy. They can put you in transit for
6 months. Nobody has any idea where you
are, whether you're dead or alive.
And if you go on the BOP website, it
just says in transit.
To where? From where?
You're not allowed access to a phone.
You're not allowed access to email.
You're not allowed access to even a pen
and paper. Literally, nobody knows where
you are.
So, that was always a concern.
Um
I wasn't afraid of solitary, certainly.
In fact, when when threatened with
solitary, I said, "Warden, I got right
in the warden's face one day." He got in
my face, I should say,
to threaten me with solitary. And I
said, "Warden,
I have gone nose to nose with Al-Qaeda,
with Hezbollah, with the Iranians.
And you want me to be afraid of you?
I said, "Come on. Give me some credit.
And you're solitary?
I've lived in far worse places than
Loretto, Pennsylvania.
And besides, I said, "I could stand to
lose a couple of pounds.
Like, I'm not afraid of your solitary."
And then he backed off.
And then, you know, one of the Italians
told me something funny one day.
He mentioned He He was talking to a
guard, and this guard was like a tough
guy. He was the only guard who wore a
stab vest because he was so unpopular.
He was pretty confident somebody was
going to stab him at some point.
And so,
the Italian said, um
"What uh what housing unit you going to
be in for the next quarter?" And he
said, "I'm going to I'm going to be in
Central 1." And he said, "Oh, my buddy
John's in Central 1." And he says,
"John, the CIA guy?"
And my friend said, "Yeah."
And the guard says, "I never with
that guy."
And the Italian said, "Yeah? Why not?"
And he said, "That's all I need. Work 8
hours and then go outside and see CNN
standing next to my car? No, thanks." I
did a Freedom of Information Act request
on myself while I was there. I have a
whole chapter about it in the book.
And um most of it was garbage. It was
250 pages. It was like my visitors list,
my medical records, just dumb stuff.
But then, there were there were
four pages, six pages that were clearly
marked
"FOIA exempt. Do not release to inmate."
And either somebody was so stupid that
they couldn't read at the Bureau of
Prisons FOIA office, or or they took
pity on me and thought that I should
have access to this. But one of the
things that stood out was this memo. It
was from a week before I arrived, and it
was to It was from the warden to all
staff telling them that I I coming. And
these big block letters it said caution
inmate has access to the media.
That's what they were afraid of. They
they said something that was so petty
that the reason why I wasn't in a a
minimum security camp, which is where
the judge ordered that I go,
was because I was trained in escape
techniques. Well, first of all,
you watch too many movies because there
is no training in escape techniques.
Secondly,
um
I knew what you were afraid of because
the FOIA request. You were afraid that I
talk to the press, and I said to the
warden one day, I said, "You know, this
whole thing backfired on you because if
I had gone to the camp, I would have
kept my my head down, I would have done
my 23 months, and I would have gone home
quietly. But you had to make a big
production out of it."
Well, I said, "When I entered this
prison, I never gave up my
constitutional rights to freedom of
expression, freedom of press, freedom of
speech.
And so, I'm going to say yes to every
interview that is requested of me."
And I did. CNN, ABC News, Atlantic
Monthly, The Economist, Playboy, Time
Magazine, NPR twice. I said yes to
everybody.
And then Jake Tapper came up one day to
interview me, and the warden was sitting
next to me,
and he said, "What's what's your biggest
challenge day-to-day?" And I said,
"Dealing with wards like this."
And I pointed at the at the warden.
He just sat there
like that. I know that like a lot of
people who are in prison, they they can
be very manipulative themselves. They've
gotten there for manipulating other
people. How did How did you like learn
who you could trust and who you couldn't
trust, um you know, you know, based on
that?
Well, I had a little bit of help. My my
uh my attorneys were very helpful before
I got there. Um one of them said
uh
he said, "Listen, you need to be really
alert." He said, "The The
is furious that your sentence is so
short and so they're going to try to set
you up. They want you to do at least 5
years and they're going to set you up so
beware.
I was there about 6 months. There was an
Afghan-American
um pharmacist a couple of cells down
from me.
And uh he had an oxy problem so he was
doing 6 years and he came up to me one
day really nice guy. He came up to me
one day and he said, "Hey John, um the
the spokesman for the Taliban wants to
meet you. He just got transferred here."
I said, "The spokesman for the Taliban?
Are you talking about that case from New
Jersey?"
And he said, "Yeah." I said, "I don't
want to talk to that guy. I got nothing
to say to that guy." And he goes, "Oh,
okay. I'll tell him."
Couple of days later I'm walking around
the track outside and this like guy with
a beard down to his waist
obviously Afghan is walking right toward
me with his hand out like to shake my
hand. And I put my hands up and I said,
"Don't touch me."
And as soon as I said that I looked past
him
and there's a guard in the woods outside
the fence with a camera with a
long-range
uh
uh scope and he's going click click
click click click click click click
click click and I said, "Touch me and
I'm going to
break your arm off."
And he's like, "Come on, man. We have a
lot in common." I said, "We don't have
anything in common except for the fact
that I tried to kill people like you.
Don't touch me."
And then he walked away. He was only in
the prison for a week and they
transferred him out. So that was their
attempt to set me up. And then you know,
otherwise and I say this early on in the
book, don't trust anybody.
Mark Lazzalotti was worthy of my trust.
And he was the only person that I
trusted.
How did this all impact your family?
Yeah, I no longer have my family.
That's the toll that it took on my
family.
Yeah.
So, no relationship with your kids or
anything like that? Barely.
Yeah. There's one one of my kid I have
five kids. I have four boys and a girl.
One of the boys I'm really close to. We
talk almost every day.
But the rest is is just uh
very difficult. Is it because of like
the media attention around this and
their their maybe their their
embarrassment or is it because of lies
that were spread? Like what's the Yeah.
Yeah, mostly. Yes.
Um
So, what was like the turning point for
you in prison? Like how did you use that
experience like to your advantage? I
decided very early on that this was
worthy of a book.
And so, you know, everybody in prison's
writing a book. And it's funny.
Um one of the guards even made fun of
me. He's like, "Oh, you're writing a
book?" And I go, "Yeah." He goes, "Every
in prison writes a book." And I said,
"But no
has made number five on the New York
Times bestsellers list."
Which is what my first book did.
So, like don't don't talk down to me,
idiot.
So, I started writing. But then they
would raid my cell and they would
confiscate what I had written.
So, what I started doing is every single
day I would write. And then when I was
done writing, I would fold it up, put it
in an envelope, mark it legal mail,
which they can't mess with, and send it
to my attorney. And she just held it for
me. I ended up writing large swaths of
the book twice because I couldn't
remember, did I write that or did I just
think it, you know?
So, um
So, I sent everything to my attorney.
When I got out of prison, I just hired a
Georgetown student to transcribe it, and
then I started the editing. I sent it to
my agent. And then the agent got it
placed. It was published by Simon and
Schuster, Rare Bird Books, and um um
yeah, and it won two literary awards.
So,
having something to focus on like that
every day, I had to focus and write. I
told myself that I wouldn't get up until
I had written 500 words and then gotten
it sent off to the lawyer.
So, that was what I did.
And so, would your lawyer then have to
relay it to the CIA to make sure that
they were cool with everything so that
you wouldn't get in more trouble? I did
that when I was all done. Okay. She just
held it. She didn't even open the the
envelopes. She just held them for me.
Did you ever have any like regret? I
mean, you've shared that you've
essentially lost your family. You've put
you were put through the wringer. You
went through so much stress and chaos.
Do you have regret in in doing what you
did now? Never a moment's regret. The
only real mistake that I made was not
hiring an attorney before blowing the
whistle. That's what I should have done.
I should have had the attorney sitting
next to me when I did it, but otherwise,
no. Like substantively, no. No regrets
at all. Nothing. And so, the main
whistleblowing moment was on that TV
interview, right? Yeah. Yeah, it was ABC
News in December of 2007. Now, were they
held accountable at all, too, or just
you? No, because they were media. So,
there was nothing that anybody
could do to them. So, how can the
average person utilize Like like Let me
rephrase this. So, like CIA guys or
former CIA guys have become very popular
on podcasts now. And I think it's
because there's something that I think
the average person thinks they can learn
from people that are spies, people that
are intelligence officers, people that
have learned how to quote-unquote like
hack the system.
Um like how can the everyday person use
some of the CIA skills that you've
developed? Oh, yeah. Um
and there are a lot of skills that can
be used in day-to-day life.
Yeah. Um you know, I think the most
important one on a day-to-day basis is
independent thinking. I really do. Like
critical analytic thinking. We're so
bombarded with propaganda from the
right, from the left, from overseas, and
you know, if you don't tow the Netanyahu
line, you're anti-Semitic, and it's just
gotten ridiculous. It's completely out
of hand.
So, you've got to be able to think
clearly for yourself
to discern what's real and what's not
real, what's propaganda, what's truth,
and then come to your own conclusions.
That's the most important. But then
there there are others. You know, I I
did a bunch of these
tongue-in-cheek.
Uh I I mentioned to you
I mentioned to you
earlier in our conversation
um
uh admit nothing, deny everything, make
counter-accusations.
And that was
that was a joke. I mean, we We that was
even emblazoned on coffee mugs at the
CIA. That was just a joke.
But there were other ones
that I that I mentioned, like
let others do your dirty work.
Or
or um
seek and utilize available cover.
You know, one of the things that you
learn to do
at the very first sign of trouble
is to
run back to your cell
because
you're going to be
hauled down to the lieutenant's office,
and they're going to want to know what
you saw. Here it is. What you saw,
you know, who did what to whom, and
you're not a rat.
So, I learned to seek and utilize
available cover.
Uh another one is um
recruit spies to steal secrets and use
those secrets to improve your position.
Uh here's another one.
Let me find a better one.
Um
cultivate relationships.
Know that everybody is working for
somebody. Adapt to your current
environment.
Um
I mean there were there were like 20 of
them. Listening is always a better
strategy than talking. Never I outshine
the boss. Be the power behind the
throne. If stability is not to your
benefit, chaos is your friend.
Find out what the target wants and use
it to your advantage. Hide in plain
sight. Use the subtle art of
misdirection. Trust no one. Never
underestimate the power of rumor.
Always maintain a plausible cover for
action and know your enemy.
Um I mean all of those can be applied in
just normal daily life.
Not even in in a prison, you know, just
in a prison where you're in constant
danger of, you know,
being walloped for reasons you'll never
understand. Let's talk about the
critical thinking part cuz that kind of
goes back to the beginning where I said
I asked if we were kind of living in
this simulation cuz there's almost
there's all this news that's just in in
inbound to people.
How can people take back
control of their minds to be able to
think critically outside of just
reading, you know, different news sites?
You know,
I wish there was an easy answer to that.
And there is no easy answer to that.
Some people
some people are so steeped in their
personal ideology
that they just seek out information that
helps to confirm their their already
currently held positions.
You know, for example, I I belong to a
men's group. Um and uh it's a it's a
fraternity. And um
almost everybody, literally almost
everybody in the group is a retired
colonel or lieutenant colonel in the
military. I mean I live in northern
Virginia, that's just the way it is.
And all they watch all day long is Fox
News.
Or some of them say, "Oh, Fox is too far
to the left." And they watch OAN or
Newsmax or whatever.
Okay, well, that's not going to help you
learn anything. It's just reinforcing
your own, you know, your own little
world.
I watch Fox and CNN and MSNBC and BBC
and Al Jazeera.
Cuz I want to hear what everybody's got
to say. Frankly,
hearing what everybody has to say helps
me hone my own positions.
And I've changed my personal positions
on issues just because
some of these broadcasts have convinced
me that my previously held position was
wrong.
Right? I mean, what kind of what kind of
intellect are you supposed to be if you
refuse to admit when you're wrong?
That doesn't help anybody. And frankly,
it just makes you look silly.
So, that's what I tell people all the
time. Never ever be wedded to one news
network. Read everything. Listen to
everybody. And I think that people, they
worry about being
manipulated, too. And I think that's
like a CIA skill that's been very
popular to talk about is how do you
protect yourself from
being manipulated? Like what are some of
the things that people can do when
they're in conversation to protect
themselves from that? If you're a person
who has had access to classified
information, you mean? I think in in
general, how can somebody protect
themselves by being manipulated from
somebody in everyday conversation? You
know, sometimes it's not possible to
protect yourself from being manipulated.
Yeah, I I was on the Sean Hannity
podcast yesterday. And I was a little
bit nervous cuz I'd never done Hannity.
He's like the last of the really giant
podcasts in America that I've
that I have wanted to do. And I've got
I've got some very well-placed friends
um including at Fox who warned me,
"He's going to come out swinging. He's
not a fan of yours. This is going to be
a tough one." So, I you know, I don't
prepare for these things cuz I figured
if I don't know these issues by now, I'm
never ever going to know them.
And I'm confident enough in my own
positions. And I'm I'm
I'm not too um
arrogant to admit when I'm wrong.
So, I went on the podcast.
I argued my side, not as forcefully as I
have in you know, in other instances,
but I argued my side. And halfway
through the podcast he said, "You know,
I was fully prepared to not like you."
And I said, "Oh, I'm sorry to hear that.
I like you."
And he said, "No, I I like you and I I
want you to come back." I said, "I would
love to come back." So, they posted it
almost immediately.
I'm going to say
less than 24 hours later they posted it.
It's a long interview. It's over an hour
and 30 minutes.
And um
and three friends of mine, independently
of one another,
texted me to say that they had just
watched it and that they were proud that
I saw his attempts to manipulate me and
I fended them off.
I didn't
I didn't even notice any attempts to
manipulate me.
To me it was just a conversation.
So, if it's hard for even somebody like
me who's been trained in this kind of
thing to not even recognize an attempt
at manipulation,
you know, how's the average person going
to do it? It's it's very very difficult.
So, what was that conversation like?
Like could you feel his energy? Was it
just kind of hostile towards you at the
beginning and then it shifted midway
through? It was not hostile at the
beginning. It was
it was
aggressive.
Aggressive, but not hostile.
I will say he interrupts a lot.
And so just as I'm getting on this train
of thought that I I need to make my
point, he he would jump in and switch
the subject.
So that was a little bit frustrating.
But but that's okay cuz it ended up
being, you know, a a spirited
conversation. I think a a skill that
you've probably learned is how to have
thought-provoking conversations with
people and stand your ground without
losing your cool.
Like how can how can the average person
get better at that? Yeah, that's a
that's a good question. I'll tell you
I'm I'm a regular on the Piers Morgan
show.
And I can't tell you how many times
people have just like taking off the
microphone and getting up and walking
out. It's like, really?
It's just a conversation.
What are you getting all huffy about and
you get up and walk out?
If you if you believe what you're saying
and
you say it in a conversational tone, but
somebody responds to you with hostility,
that's on them.
It doesn't hurt you in any way. Like if
somebody loses his cool and calls me an
ass, okay, maybe I am an but
but that's on you if you can't handle
what it is that I'm saying.
So I just kind of
you know,
state my case,
defend myself. Andrew W.K.
and I did a debate on uh
on uh the Danny Jones podcast about a
year and a half ago.
And
it was a like I said earlier, spirited.
It was a spirited debate.
I put him in an intellectual box in a
corner
at one point and he lashed out
and he got nasty.
And um and I I just wouldn't concede. I
just kept going back to my my analytic
points. When I got home that night, Alan
Dershowitz called me.
Alan Dershowitz, the professor emeritus
of the Harvard Law School,
uh
advisor to
Donald Trump.
Dershowitz called me and said
that he had just watched the podcast and
he said, "You gave that kid a master
class on the Constitution."
And I said, "I'm so glad that you see it
that way because I felt like his
arguments were irrational."
And he said, "They were. He hadn't
thought them through."
But Andrew's a smart guy. He knows he's
a smart guy and he thinks that his
intelligence can get him out of
of debates where he hasn't really fully
thought through his positions.
So, if you're going to take a position
on something
and you're unwilling
to
allow someone else to cause you to
change your mind, man, you better be
100%
sure that you can defend that position
because if you can't, you're going to
look foolish. But this is a skill that I
feel like you've had to sharpen because
a a lot of people
they would fall they would default to
people pleasing because they get so
nervous or scared. They don't want the
conversation to go bad or they don't
have the confidence in their position to
kind of stand there or
they get rattled and then when you get
rattled, then it's easier for that other
person to kind of just sit there and
just keep throwing jabs at you because
you're already emotionally rattled. Is
there like I mean I
Do you do anything like meditation or
breath work? Like how do you how have
you gotten to the point where you can
have these conversations and just be
even-keeled even when people are
trashing you? You know what it is, Doug?
It's
making the same arguments
sometimes multiple times a day
since 2007.
That's what it is.
This has become my life. Debating people
is my life.
Sometimes I will appear on as many as
six podcasts in a day. I've cut back
like seriously since
since my popularity has risen. Um just
cuz there aren't enough hours in the
day.
But
but I have made these arguments so many
times. I have been hit with every
question
a person could possibly think of
that it's made me that confident in my
position that
you know, I just go with it. How can
somebody tell if they're being lied to?
Is it Is it easier than than the
manipulation?
Uh yeah. It's funny that you ask. I
actually wrote a book called The CIA
Insider's Guide to Lying and Lie
Detection.
>> [laughter]
>> Um there are a couple of physical tells.
People will look down when answering or
they'll look up as if they're reading a
script that they're preparing for
themselves in their minds. They fidget.
They clear their throat, which is a
delaying tactic even just for a second.
Um
and the deeper you go into a
conversation, if they lose their train
of thought or contradict themselves,
it's because they can't keep the lie
straight. So going into a conversation,
let's take it two ways. One where you
know the person's going to lie to you
and the other one where
you catch them in a lie mid-sentence.
If if let's just say you catch someone
doing something. Let's just say you
catch your partner cheating on you and
you know that they're going to lie to
you about this.
When you go into that conversation, like
the playbook? You know, as Sergeant Joe
Friday used to say, "Just the facts,
ma'am."
Just hit them with the facts. Listen,
I've been in this situation more than
once.
And when when they immediately go to
gaslighting, you know you've got them.
"Are you cheating on me?" "You are
mentally ill, you know that? You are
mentally ill." Okay, so you are cheating
on me.
You know, they just go over the top in
defense. And then is the goal to
expose them, or is the goal to just
prove your point and then walk away and
not
>> That's it right there.
Prove your point, walk away. You can't
go back in time. You're not going to
convince them to take responsibility for
their actions. You have to immediately
reset yourself
to self-protection.
That's what it comes down to. You know,
you mentioned Andrew Bustamante, I love
him. He's been on the show a few times.
I know you guys have had your
differences.
One of the things I learned from him
about lying, and I'd love to get your
thoughts, is that it's about pattern
recognition. Like you have to
consistency with someone to see how they
behave, and if they start to behave a
little differently or speak differently,
then there's a chance they may be lying.
Like is that Would you say Would you
agree with that is a good tactic? Yeah,
I agree with that. And you know, one of
the one of the best examples is in
Godfather II between Michael Corleone
and Fredo, his older but less
less able brother.
Um
there's one scene where where Michael
First of all, Michael is angry at Fredo
because of the way Fredo questioned him
in the presence of Moe Greene, if you
remember, over the sale of a of a casino
in Las Vegas. And then later in the
film,
uh, Michael asks Fredo if he knows
so-and-so. And he says, "No, I don't
know him. I never met him." And then
still later,
he mentions that person. Fredo mentions
the person that he claimed not to know
and said that they went all over Havana
together and that that guy knows all the
best clubs in Havana.
That's how Michael knew that Fredo had
had, um,
turned on him. And he gave him sort of
the kiss of Judas and said, "I knew it
was you, Fredo."
And it was because of the
change in in Fredo's pattern of
responding to his brother's questions.
Yeah, because it's
you're so right cuz the way I I
understand it as well is it's like you
you mentioned the delays and if
somebody's clearing their throat or if
they contradict themselves,
but somebody might just talk like that
where they stutter, you know, often no
matter if they're telling the truth or
not, but if they then they But the truth
is the truth.
And that won't or that shouldn't change.
So if you're mid conversation with
somebody and you catch them in a lie,
like how do you
take the conversation further so that
either you get them to admit that they
were lying if they're not like some sort
of sociopath or,
um,
you prove your point and you can walk
away.
It depends on the person that you're
arguing with or debating. If if we're
talking about a cheating spouse,
no, I I wouldn't I wouldn't call her on
the lie. I would certainly make a note
of it, probably a written note, and then
look for the best divorce divorce
attorney money could buy, which is
exactly what I did. Um,
if it's if it's something professional,
at the CIA, if you're, you know, trying
to recruit a spy to steal a secret,
everybody's going to be lying to you.
And so you have to sort of take that
into consideration. But then, you know,
you have tools at the CIA that you don't
have in in regular life. Like
I think this guy lies to me all the
time. I think he's lying about his
access. So I'm going to strap him to the
polygraph, and we're going to get to the
bottom of this today.
And if he's lying, he's cut off. He's
fired. We call it terminated, but it's
an unfortunate word. That just means
he's fired, and we we end our
relationship.
If it's a friend, well, you know, make a
mental note. So-and-so's not reliable.
He's lying to me. I know he's lying to
me. I generally don't call people out on
lying, except when I was at the agency,
and it was a source lying to me.
I'd call them out then. And I think
people that are either lied to or
they're manipulated or they start to go
down these echo chambers, and they don't
even realize it.
Like how does that happen? Yeah.
And I I I
I think
probably the easiest way to describe it
is
is when people feel that they can get
away with their lies, or they feel like
they're smart enough that they can build
up a lie and then maintain the lie.
George Santos, this former congressman,
he was congressman for 15 minutes from
Long Island.
He was a serial fabulist. He lied about
literally everything in life.
Literally everything.
And um, you know, it caught up with him,
and he ended up in prison, and then he
got like 7 years. He was in prison for a
few months, and and Trump pardoned him.
But
you can't build a life on lies. It's not
sustainable. It's eventually going to
just
all come tumbling down. And I think that
people who lie,
if they're not careful, they'll be like,
"Oh, what's the danger of a little white
lie here and there?"
And then if it becomes your personality,
then you just become known as a liar,
which isn't good. My first station chief
told me one time at the agency, "Never,
ever lie to medical, security, or
finance because not only will they ruin
your career,
they can put you in prison."
And he said, "And I'll add to that,
never lie to me."
And I I always thought those were good
words to live by. Yeah, and bring it in.
Speaking of cheating, I mean, there's a
rule that I have
that I if I find out you're like
actively cheating on your spouse,
emotionally, physically, I don't care
what it is. Like I won't keep you in my
circle whatsoever because if you're
doing that to the person that you're
like sleeping with and laying next to,
like what are you going to do to me?
Yeah, exactly right. I feel exactly the
same way. You're somebody that strikes
me you'd be hard
to manipulate based on your experience,
what you've learned, what you survived.
What's the easiest type of person who
often gets manipulated? Someone who has
an identifiable vulnerability.
Vulnerability is an important word at
the CIA. A vulnerability can mean almost
anything. Anything that can be exploited
to get you to do what I want.
So, maybe the vulnerability is
you want more money.
It's as easy as that. You just want more
money. And so, I give you a monthly
salary and in exchange you give me
information.
But the vulnerability could be something
as genuine as
you just really, really love your kids.
And you want your kids to go to
Harvard, let's say, instead of, you
know, the local college in Cameroon or
wherever we happen to be.
I'll get your kids into Harvard.
But you have to do what I what I want
you to do.
Another vulnerability may be um
you got passed over for promotion one
too many times and you're so pissed off
at your boss that you want to get
revenge on him.
And so you'll give me
classified information just to screw
your boss.
I mean, usually it's money. Sometimes
it's love of family. There was one guy
who was very well placed who gave me the
kitchen sink
because his wife had breast cancer and
he really really wanted her to go to the
Mayo Clinic.
And so we put her in the Mayo Clinic.
Yeah, so it's it's all about
vulnerabilities and and not in a bad
way.
I just need to identify something that
you want.
I give it to you and in exchange you
give me what I want. Yeah, because at
the end of the day it's finding out what
drives them and what motivates them
to move forward and using that
to your advantage. That's exactly right.
What's been something that you've
done over the course of your life when
you've manipulated somebody that you
look back and you feel bad you feel bad
about? Yeah, there was one person
professionally.
Lovely lady, older lady. She's long dead
now.
I I was working with a source
who was so sensitive
I could not risk meeting him
in
hotels or restaurants.
We just could not be seen in public
together.
So what we would normally do
would be to meet at 2:00 in the morning.
I would find some deserted place
like the parking lot of a closed factory
at 2:00 in the morning and we would meet
there.
And then I I decided that for security
reasons, you know, any cop could be
driving through the parking lot at any
given time just to make sure kids aren't
there, you know, doing drugs or breaking
windows or whatever.
That even meeting at the parking lot at
2:00 in the morning was too risky. So, I
wanted to rent a safe house. Well,
why would an accredited diplomat be
renting an apartment?
Right? I mean, that you can't do that.
That would raise all kinds of red flags.
That would identify me as a CIA officer.
So, I had to recruit what's called a
safe house keeper.
I recruit somebody whose sole job it is
to just go out and rent me an apartment
in his or her name.
Keep it clean.
Keep it stocked with, you know, water.
And I use it one night a week for 2
hours.
And otherwise, it just sits empty.
And this woman just did not want to do
it.
And I cajoled, and I argued, and I
sweet-talked, and she finally agreed to
do it.
And then, um
and then she had like like some kind of
nervous breakdown.
Like, she didn't even know what I was
going to use it for. I think she
probably thought I was cheating on my
wife, and that's why I wanted this, you
know, pied-à-terre. That wasn't it at
all.
But, um
she ended up
having some sort of a breakdown, and she
had to leave the country and move back
to the United States, and her family
took care of her. And I always wondered
if
if that was because I pressured her too
much. Are you taught to not have remorse
or regret when you do things like that?
And you really convince yourself. I
mean, the whole culture convinces you
that that that we're the good the good
guys.
We're all the good guys. We're do This
is This is God's work. We're doing it
for Uncle Sam and to keep Americans
safe, and
you know, don't ever question yourself.
We're the good guys. You've dealt with a
lot of pressure both from your career,
prison, even like what you're doing with
what you're doing now. Like what do you
lean on mentally when you get
overwhelmed? Music, exercise,
really great movies.
You have to be able to just completely
shut it off and do something totally
different. I recommend to people all the
time
music, exercise, and movies. Immerse
yourself. Go to the gym, go for a run,
listen to an hour or two of
uninterrupted music. You know,
headphones. Don't answer the phone.
Don't surf the the internet.
Just do something for yourself.
And it's hard, you know, everybody's
busy, everybody's
wired electronically to different
devices, and it's hard, but it's
important. What's your go-to like music
or a movie to watch if you've just
gotten in like a war with somebody on
Twitter?
Don't laugh at me. Um but
I listen to
a lot of classic rock.
Mostly early to mid-70s classic rock.
Um I listen to folk
specifically from the '30s and '40s and
'50s.
And more than anything else probably I
listen to Greek music. There's a There's
a genre of Greek music that came out of
the prisons and the opium dens of
Constantinople around the turn of the
20th century called Rebetika.
It's a Greek like blues is is the way
most people describe it. And and mostly
I listen to that. So classic rock like
Zeppelin, the Eagles, stuff like that?
Definitely. Definitely.
Love it. What's your workout routine
like to keep your mind sane? Only in the
last year I've gotten so busy that I I
gave up my gym membership.
But um now I I go for very long walks.
But I I go with earbuds, so I'm not
distracted by by people or by traffic or
things like that. So I do a lot of
walking.
Um before I used to I used to go to the
gym
almost every day.
Yeah. And you start, you know, 15
minutes on the treadmill just to warm
up, and then you got to do you got to do
weights. It's all about muscle tone.
You don't want to just shrivel up and
you know,
blow away.
How important do you think uh exercise
and your overall health is um for things
like mindset, confidence? Critical.
Absolutely critical.
Um
you almost can't work at the CIA and not
have PTSD.
In fact, I I've got a buddy
we go to the same church, we're in the
same men's group, and we also worked at
the CIA together.
And consummate overachiever, he's also a
brigadier general in the army and a
psychiatrist.
Yeah, so he's done everything.
And he said to me one time,
"I find it fascinating
that you came back from Pakistan with no
PTSD.
But you have crippling PTSD from your
divorce."
And I said, "I allowed myself,
despite my training,
to trust one person.
And that was the person who betrayed
me."
He diagnosed me with something called
moral injury, which is a a relatively
new diagnosis. It appears in the DSM 6.
And um
I had never heard of it. I had to look
it up.
And what it comes down to is if you're
raised in a certain
way
to believe that these things are right
and these things are wrong. And the
wrong things you just don't do and then
somebody does it to you.
Your brain cannot wrap itself around the
fact that this has been done to you.
And it leads to PTSD. From what I've
gathered it was it was a very high
conflict divorce, very stressful for
you. And which so would you
kind of agree in the fact that that
situation was harder than everything you
went through with leaving the CIA?
Oh, my my divorce was the was the worst
thing I ever went through in my life.
Far, far worse than prison, far worse
than being arrested and
and yeah, any of that stuff. Far more
difficult than going after Al-Qaeda or
the Iranians or Hezbollah or
any of the things I ever did at the CIA.
And just because of the the the moral
part of it for you. Yeah, you want to
you want to have like one person in life
that you can trust. Just one.
Is that asking too much?
Yeah, I never thought so. I think that
people have a hard time dealing with
stress and anxiety.
Um
what are some of your tips for how
people can not get overwhelmed when
things aren't going their way? Yeah,
you've got to this is one of the things
that they taught us at the agency, too.
You've got to do things for yourself.
You know,
take up a hobby. I have no hobbies. I
honest to God, I'm not just blowing
smoke here. I'm the hardest working
person I know.
I I work easily 16 hours a day. I
actually set my alarm for 4:00 a.m. just
so I can answer Cameo requests until
7:00 and then start my regular work day.
Um
but I have no hobbies. I used to, but I
don't. So, I decided to take up a hobby.
I took up astrophotography, right?
Photographing the planets and then
nebula and galaxies and stuff like that.
And it requires great patience.
And so, that's actually worked out for
me.
But, you know, go get a massage, go to
the gym,
go go swimming at the YMCA or whatever.
Do something. Go biking. You know, now
electronic bikes are everywhere. There's
no reason that everybody shouldn't be
biking.
Because you don't even have to pedal
uphill anymore. It's all electronic.
So, you got to do something for
yourself. You got to block off time for
yourself. Otherwise, you burn out and
you go crazy. What about like if
something
stressful happens like in the moment?
Like how can people zone out from that?
Yeah. You know, three people over the
last 3 days have recommended meditation
to me.
Um I've never I've never meditated. My
brother swears by it.
And other people that I've spoken to say
it's the greatest thing that that they
ever took up. So, there there's got to
be something to it. You know, there's
something that's popular in my area
right now, and it's these um
stretching clinics.
Right? Where you pay like 50 bucks and
then they stretch the heck out of your
body.
And I'm told that that is like supremely
relaxing and excellent. I haven't tried
it myself. I will say that I've broken
the piggy bank and I've
I've gone to get massages for the very
first time in my life.
And there
I I'm not even sure I can come up with
something that is
more satisfying
and
feels better than getting a massage. I
mean, you've been through so much. Like
have you gone to therapy or anything to
deal with some of the trauma? Oh,
absolutely.
Absolutely.
It's funny. I I like I say, I never had
PTSD from from the agency. Never.
Um but my divorce just destroyed me.
Like what's your mission now? Like I
mean is your main is your main mission
now what you're doing with the podcast
and and interviews and speaking about
like current events?
Yes. I've been extraordinarily fortunate
in the last 8 weeks or so in that I gave
an interview to uh
to Steven uh Bartlett at uh Diary of a
CEO.
And a 20-year-old sophomore from the
University of Texas at Austin took that
interview and chopped it up into shorts
and gave me an Alvin and the Chipmunks
voice and had laser beams shooting out
of my eyes.
All in good fun.
And it just went crazy.
Viral on Tik Tok
to the point where I'm not exaggerating
when I tell you I can't walk 25 ft down
the street without somebody stopping me
and asking for a selfie. And I always
say yes.
Always. I flew from Miami last night to
Washington. I got stopped five times at
the airport and twice on the plane
and asked for selfies.
So
out of that came representation by a
major talent agency.
Um
invitations for
speeches and you know, new publishing
deals and
I'm wrapped in Hollywood. Um
I'm going to be the spokesman for you
know, this company or that company or
the other company. It's just my whole
life has changed in the last 8 weeks.
So the anchor of that is is my podcast.
And um
and I've got my books.
For many years as as a hobby until a
couple of years ago when I ran out of
time, I would write television pilots
and I've been fortunate enough to sell
eight of them over the last 20 years in
Hollywood. So I've I've got a manager
and an agent and an entertainment
attorney and
that's fun to do. So I'm just going to
keep writing and podcasting and speaking
and
and call that my career.
What's your message to people who
I mean, your
turning point was a pretty hard turn,
right? But a lot of people they they
have these turning points where they
lose a job or they get divorced or maybe
they have to go to rehab for 6 months
and they feel like they're stuck.
What's your message to them based on
what you've learned about your own
journey? Yeah, you're you're actually
not stuck. It feels like it, but things
really do get better. They really do.
You know, let me tell you a story, too.
Have you ever heard of the folk singer
Pete Seeger?
You You have. You have. You just don't
know it.
All the songs from our our youth that we
learned in kindergarten, those are all
Pete Seeger songs. Anyway, um Pete told
me a story one time about the folk
singer Phil Ochs. Phil Ochs was huge in
the '60s and '70s.
Phil um
Phil was
on a tour of Africa
to sing and put on concerts and he got
mugged.
And the mugger cut his cut his throat.
And he lived, but he was no longer able
to sing high notes.
And he went into a deep depression.
One night, Pete was performing at the
Cafe Wha? in Greenwich Village
and he had to literally run to Grand
Central Station to catch the last train
to Beacon, New York, which is where he
lived. It was the last train of the
night. So just as he's packing up his
banjo and he's going to physically run
to Grand Central,
Phil Ochs calls and one of the
waitresses says, "Pete, Phil Ochs is on
the phone for you."
And he grabs the phone, he said, "Phil,
I can't talk. I've got to run and catch
the last train to Beacon." And he he
said, "Call me tomorrow." And he hung
up.
And Phil Ochs killed himself.
He wanted to be talked out of it.
And Pete said,
"That selfish prick." He said, "I'll
never forgive him."
He had no idea how much he was hurting
the people who meant the most to him.
So, you know, when you're feeling at
your lowest,
like you're never going to claw your way
out of this, first of all, that's just
simply not true.
It really does get better.
But,
you have no idea
how loved you are
and how much you would hurt
the people that you care about the most.
I had a friend, James.
James did some really stupid when he was
young.
And he ended up
he ended up doing a 17 years of a
20-year sentence.
And
I mean, it's hard enough to get a job
when you you've got a a felony
conviction. If you have a violent felony
conviction, you're never going to work,
not in any meaningful way.
And so, he went overseas.
Uh he was really ripped. He used to used
to lift every day, so he went into porn
for a while, and he just he things just
weren't working out for him.
And he decided that he was going to
commit suicide. But, he didn't want to
make a mess in his mother's house. So,
he took a gun, he drove to a Walmart
parking lot to kill himself. And just as
he puts the gun into his mouth,
an off-duty ATF agent pulls into the
next space. He just finished his shift,
and he's going to go into Walmart to do
his grocery shopping.
Pulls out his gun. Drop the gun. Drop
the gun.
James says, "You don't understand. I'm
I'm going to kill myself. I'm not going
to rob the the
Walmart." Anyway, the ATF agent disarmed
him. They charged him with felon with a
gun. It's a mandatory minimum sentence
of 8 years.
But, he got out on bail. And he used to
call me every single day and say, "I'm
going to kill myself. I'm going to kill
myself. I'm going to kill myself." And
I'd say, "James, you say this every day.
You're not going to kill yourself.
You're going to relax. You're going to
do what your attorney tells you to do."
I said, "Buddy, take a break. Fly out
here. I'm in DC. He was in Montana. Uh
fly out here for a week or two and just
decompress. And we can talk about
everything. You're going to get past it.
You're not going to get
felon with a gun. You know, the the
attorney's going to argue, you know,
mental strain and
Well,
on July 4th
of 2023,
his sister was lighting a firecracker
and it went off in her hand and it blew
two of her fingers off.
So, he calls me and he says, "My sister
had this accident with a firecracker.
She's in surgery now. They're trying to
sew her fingers back on."
And I said, "Oh my god, that's terrible.
I'll send flowers. Tell her, you know,
hope
everything works out okay." And I said,
"But, you sound awfully good." And he
said, "Yeah, I feel really good. I feel
really good about things." I said,
"Great. Great."
Two days later, his sister calls me. And
I said, "Oh my god, how are you doing?"
She said, "I'm okay. It was a long
surgery. They reattached my fingers.
That's not why I'm calling."
She said, "James killed himself last
night."
And I was like, "What?" I said, "Why
would he do that?"
I said, "I just talked to him 2 days
ago. He sounded great."
And she said, "He sounded great because
he had made up his mind to do it."
And he left a note.
And he said to his mother,
"Call John and tell him I said I was
sorry."
And I felt just like Pete Seeger felt
with Phil Ochs, you selfish bastard.
How could you do this?
I told you a thousand times, call me.
Call me if you're thinking of doing
something like that.
And he didn't.
He walked down to a neighbor's house,
strung up a noose in an oak tree, and he
hung himself.
And just like Pete said, "I'll never
forgive him for doing that."
But anyway, things really do get better.
There are a thousand people out there
who want the best for you and who are
willing to take a phone call and be a a
friendly ear.
Rely on the people around you. Rely on
your friends and family.
That's what I would say. Was there ever
a moment for you where you felt hopeless
and down and dumped like that?
Yeah, the night that I got arrested. And
my and my wife talked me out of it.
I had five kids at home, too. What was
that moment like where you just where
just at that moment your world was
coming crashing down on you? She um we
were watching TV the night of my arrest
and uh she said she said, "Let's let's
go to bed. This has been a terrible day.
Let's just go to bed." And I said, "No,
you go to bed. I'm going to watch some
more TV." And I wasn't going to watch
TV. I was going to go down into the
garage and start the car and just lay
across the backseat.
And I think she suspected it.
And she said, "No,
let's go to bed."
And she stood there until I finally shut
off the TV and got up and and we went to
bed. Then you got arrested that night?
No, no. I got arrested that morning.
That's why I was so upset. Like looking
back, knowing what you know now, what
would you have told your
self that day, knowing what you know
now? You can tough this out.
This is not going to be as bad as you
think it is. In fact, my brother said
something to me the day of my arrest. He
said, "I know you can't see it,
but this is going to turn out to be the
best thing that ever happened to you."
And he was right.
As crazy as it sounds,
it was the best thing that ever happened
to me. You know, I think that people
they have this internal voice
that's telling them to do something,
whether it's
to start a company, whether it's to
you know, break up with somebody,
whether it's to, you know, ask somebody
to marry them, whatever. And they don't
do it, and they don't do it. Like, what
do you think can happen to a person that
ignores their internal voice? Yeah.
And you know,
listen to that internal voice. Certainly
seek counsel from people you trust,
but listen to that internal voice. It's
important, right? It is. So, as we kind
of bring this
uh to a close, like I got to ask you, so
what do you think? What is your overall
perspective of the world right now
and what we're going through? I think
the world's in a very dangerous place
right now.
Very dangerous. You know, we've we've
got
the Russia-Ukraine war still, you know,
in a stalemate. Well, not really. The
Russians are winning, but
I mean, you'll they'll they'll fight for
weeks over 15 ft of territory.
Um we've got, you know, the US-Israeli
war against Iran, the opening and
closing and then reopening of the of the
Strait of Hormuz. Europe, yesterday I
saw breaking news, Europe has 6 weeks of
jet fuel left. It'll be an economic
calamity around the world if Europe runs
out of jet fuel.
Um in the meantime, the Chinese are
expanding by leaps and bounds.
Here in the United States, we're we're
split right down the center politically,
ideologically.
I mean, I
I've not seen anything like this,
certainly in my adult lifetime, but
I'm I'm just old enough to remember
1968, 1969. I was a kid.
Um
and things were as terrible then as they
are now. You know, Martin Luther King's
assassinated, then Bobby Kennedy's
assassinated, then Kent State, and then
the summer of love, and everybody's in
the street, and the cops are shooting
unarmed people, and
yeah. I think we're just as split now as
we were in '68 and '69. Do you think
that we're going to that do you think
that there's a bigger threat now for
like local acts of terrorism? Not
necessarily. I think what we have to be
worried about are
acts of lone wolf terrorism.
You know, somebody walking into a church
or a synagogue or a mosque and just
opening fire. You know, we've got what
is it? Like a mass shooting a day
according to the FBI's definition of a
mass shooting where three or more people
are injured every day.
I was I was giving an interview to a to
a Hungarian psychiatrist today. He's
doing a
a study on
on trauma.
And um
he told me that um he's interviewed
several FBI profilers who told him that
in the 1970s and the 1980s
so the so-called golden age of serial
killers
there was a point where there were 150
serial killers loose
killing.
Now
on any given day there are 30 serial
killers loose in America that we just
haven't caught yet.
And he and he said,
"You know, in Hungary we can't even
fathom something like this because we've
never had a serial killer. Not a single
one."
And here in the United States the first
documented serial killer began killing
in 1792.
That's crazy. I didn't know that. It's a
part of our culture. So do you think the
what do you think the average person can
do? Cuz I think you're see some people
like, "Oh, you should just move out of
the country." Like, what can just stay
here and stay informed? For better or
for worse, we have to live and work
within the system that we've created for
ourselves.
And so, yeah, be as well informed as you
possibly can be, vote your conscience,
and then demand
change from your elected officials. They
work for us, and by God, if they don't
do what we tell them to do, then we've
got to throw them out and elect somebody
else. We have to take the system
seriously, because it's the only system
that we have. John, thanks so much for
coming on the pod. Where can people
learn more about what you're doing? Oh,
thank you. Mostly, it's at
johnkiriakou.com,
but my my
two podcasts are Deep Focus on YouTube
and John Kiriakou's Dead Drop on Apple
Podcast. I'm proud to say it's in the
top 1/10 of 1% of all podcasts
worldwide.
>> [laughter]
>> Isn't that crazy? And then this is all
your popularity you said it's coming
just in the last couple months? Yeah,
the last 2 months. That's awesome, man.
Yeah, crazy. I'm very grateful.
Well, thanks again for coming on the
show, and appreciate you, and uh
yeah, and it's it's really cool It's
been really, I guess, kind of cool to
follow along with your journey and see
what you're doing now. Thank you very
much. Good to see you, Doug.